## JAYLEN WANG

Carnegie Mellon University Email: jaylenw@andrew.cmu.edu

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering Web: https://jaylenwang7.github.io

## **BRIEF BIOGRAPHY**

My work bridges computer architecture and software systems, demonstrating the importance of that bridge in enabling sustainable data center systems via solutions that span the compute stack.

As the demand for web services continues to grow, data centers are scaling up to meet the demand, consuming a massive amount of energy and producing significant carbon emissions. My research focuses on addressing the growing carbon emissions, produced both by running and manufacturing hardware, of data centers by analyzing inefficiencies across computer architecture and software systems and designing solutions to make these systems more energy and carbon efficient.

My work is one of the first to examine the environmental impact of hyperscale web systems and to provide actionable insights to reduce it. My work integrates carbon efficiency into computer system design, as it is crucial for sustainable growth and access to critical web services in both developed and developing nations. My work is a step towards curbing computing's contributions towards climate change and promoting sustainable computing practices.

My research has been recognized with the 2023 Benjamin Garver Lamme/Westinghouse Graduate Fellowship and the 2022 Carnegie Institute of Technology Dean's Fellowship.

#### **EDUCATION**

## Ph.D., Electrical and Computer Engineering

Carnegie Mellon University

Advisor: Prof. Akshitha Sriraman

Aug 2022 - Present

GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0; Benjamin Garver Lamme/Westinghouse Graduate Fellowship

Dissertation Title: Enabling Sustainable Web Systems

## B.Sc., Electrical Engineering

Harvard University Aug 2018 - May 2022

PIs: Profs. David Brooks & Gu-Yeon Wei

Minor in Computer Science

GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0; Member of Phi Beta Kappa

## AWARDS AND HONORS

NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program (GRFP) Award Winner Awarded \$171,000 as part of prestigious fellowship supporting exceptional graduate students in STEM	2023 I
Ford Foundation 2023 Predoctoral Fellowship Competition Honorable Mention Honorable mention given to top Ford Fellowship candidates	2023
Benjamin Garver Lamme/Westinghouse Graduate Fellowship Full tuition support for second year of PhD	2023
Carnegie Institute of Technology Dean's Fellow Awarded \$83,000 towards tuition, stipend, and travel	2022
Harvard SEAS Dean's Engineering Design Award Awarded \$500 for having one of the top 7 (out of 43) best Senior engineering design projects	2022
Sophia Freund Prize Awarded \$1000 as highest ranking undergraduate in the Electrical Engineering department	2022
Phi Beta Kappa Member Admitted into Harvard's chapter, one of 146 out of 1962 (7.4%) students	2022
Derek Bok Center Distinction in Teaching Awarded to most highly rated (by students) TAs; received distinction in three semesters	2020, 2021
John Harvard Scholar Award given to top 5% (4.0 GPA) of students in respective class	2020

Awarded \$3,500 to perform independent research during the summer

Detur Prize Winner

Recognizes students with top academic standing in their first year at Harvard

## PEER-REVIEWED WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS & PANELS

- Jaylen Wang, Udit Gupta, and Akshitha Sriraman. Peeling Back the Carbon Curtain: Carbon Optimization Challenges in Cloud Computing. 2nd Workshop on Sustainable Computer Systems (HotCarbon 2023). July 2023.
- Jialun Lyu, Jaylen Wang, Kali Frost, Chaojie Zhang, Celine Irvene, Esha Choukse, Rodrigo Fonseca, Ricardo Bianchini, Fiodar Kazhamiaka, and Daniel S. Berger. Myths and Misconceptions Around Reducing Embedded Carbon for Cloud Platforms. 2nd Workshop on Sustainable Computer Systems (HotCarbon 2023). July 2023.
- (Organized Panel) Jaylen Wang, Udit Gupta, and Akshitha Sriraman. Panel on Sustainable Systems. The 19th Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS 2023). Feb 2023.

Organized and moderated a panel on sustainable systems research with five expert panelists in the field.

- Jaylen Wang, Udit Gupta, and Akshitha Sriraman. Characterizing Datacenter Server Generations for Lifetime Extension and Carbon Reduction. 1st Workshop on Hot Topics in System Infrastructure (HotInfra 2023) held in conjunction with ISCA. June 2023.
- Jaylen Wang, Udit Gupta, and Akshitha Sriraman. Characterizing Datacenter Server Generations for Lifetime Extension and Carbon Reduction. 1st Workshop on NetZero Carbon Computing (NetZero 2023) held in conjunction with HPCA. Feb 2023.

Performs the first ever characterization of server generations for microservice-based web services to enable hardware lifetime extension

Introduces equity as a first-order design metric in modern data center scheduling systems

- Jaylen Wang, Abdulrahman Mahmoud, Gu-Yeon Wei, and David Brooks. A Dataflow-Aware Fault Resilience Analysis Framework for Deep Neural Network Accelerators. Young Architect Workshop (YArch 2021) held in conjunction with ASPLOS. March 2022.

Introduces a new framework and tool to quickly and accurately assess the reliability of deep neural network accelerator designs to random bit flips, providing insights for resilient accelerator design

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Azure Systems Research Intern, Microsoft Research Redmond

May 2023 - August 2023

Mentor: Fiodar Kazhamiaka

Investigating how to design better server configurations and SKUs to improve Azure's resource and carbon efficiency.

## Graduate Research Assistant, Carnegie Mellon University

Aug 2022 - Present

Advisor: Prof. Akshitha Sriraman

Introducing sustainability as a first-order hardware/software system design metric for hyperscale systems and redesigning data center systems to promote hardware reuse

#### Undergraduate Research Assistant, Harvard University

March 2021 - Aug 2022

Lab: Harvard Architecture, Circuits, and Compilers Group

Advisors: Dr. Abdulrahman Mahmoud, Profs. Gu-Yeon Wei and David Brooks

Developing a hardware-aware framework for analyzing the resilience of deep neural network accelerators to soft errors, considering the reuse of values in an accelerator's dataflow propagation

2019

## Engineering Development Group Intern, MathWorks

Team: Deep Learning HDL Toolbox Supervisors: Wang Chen, Siyuan Xu

Enabling efficient mapping of non-square convolution kernels onto square processing-element arrays, allowing users to deploy models using non-square kernels onto FPGAs

## Undergraduate Research Assistant, Harvard University

May 2020 - Aug 2020

May 2021 - Aug 2021

Lab: Harvard Edge Computing Lab Advisor: Prof. Vijay Janapa Reddi

Analyzing how using SLAM for localization affects efficiency and power usage within autonomous drone applications by integrating SLAM algorithms into an open-sourced drone benchmarking framework

#### Undergraduate Research Assistant, Harvard University

May 2019 - Aug 2019

Fall 2019

Lab: Hoffman Physics Lab Advisor: Prof. Jenny Hoffman

Developing a tensioning system for an XY-walker system to extend the range of a scanning tunneling microscope used to research the proximity effect of superconductivity

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

LEADERSHIP & VOLUNTEERING

## Undergraduate Teaching Assistant, Harvard University

– Systems Programming and Machine Organization; Prof. Eddie Kohler	Fall 2020, 2021
– Circuits, Devices, and Transduction; Profs. Gage Hills & Woodward Yang	Fall 2021
– Systems and Control; Profs. Li Na & Yue Lu	Fall 2021
– Introduction to Eletrical Engineering, Profs. Chris Lombardo & Marko Loncar	Spring 2021

# - Integration, Series and Differential Equations; Dr. Hakim Walker

- CMU Institute of Technology K-12 Outreach, STEM Volunteer	2023
– President of Harvard Club Tennis	2019-2022
– President of Harvard College Engineering Society	2020-2021
- Co-President of Harvard Engineering Peer Concentration Advisors	2020-2021

## TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages System Skills	C/C++, Python, Shell, Verilog, x86 Assembly Low-level Systems Programming, Performance Characterization,
Tools and Frameworks	Scripting, Docker Pin, gem5, Linux perf, Intel PMU tools,
10013 and 11ameworks	PyTorch, Catapult HLS, Git

## REFERENCES

- Prof. Akshitha Sriraman (akshitha@cmu.edu)
   Assistant Professor, Carnegie Mellon University
- 2. Daniel S. Berger (daberg@microsoft.com) & Fiodar Kazhamiaka (fkazhamiaka@microsoft.com) Researchers in Azure Systems Research Group, Microsoft
- 3. Prof. David Brooks (dbrooks@g.harvard.edu)
  Haley Family Professor of Computer Science, Harvard University
- 4. Prof. Udit Gupta (ugupta@cornell.edu) Assistant Professor, Cornell University
- 5. Prof. Gu-Yeon Wei (guyeon@seas.harvard.edu) Robert and Suzanne Case Professor of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Harvard